<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vindication of a late pamphlet (entituled 0bedience and submission to the present government demonstrated from Bp. Overal's Convocation-book) from the false glosses and illusive interpretations of a pretended answer / by the author of the first pamphlet.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Zachary, 1653-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37878</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17150632</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17150632</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1160:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vindication of a late pamphlet (entituled 0bedience and submission to the present government demonstrated from Bp. Overal's Convocation-book) from the false glosses and illusive interpretations of a pretended answer / by the author of the first pamphlet.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Zachary, 1653-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCI [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taylor, Zachary, 1653-1705. --  Obedience and submission to the present government.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105902:1"/>
            <p>THE VINDICATION OF A LATE PAMPHLET, (ENTITULED, Obedience and Submiſſion TO THE PRESENT GOVERNMENT, Demonſtrated from Bp. <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation-Book) From the Falſe Gloſſes, and Illuſive Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of a Pretended Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Author of the Firſt Pamphlet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms-Inn</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:105902:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105902:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MAlice</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> are very Spiteful and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Words, and ſuch as the Author had little Comfort of, ſince he ſaw them in the Printed Pamphlet; for he had learnt, That <hi>the Wrath of Man worketh not the Righteouſneſs of God;</hi> And his deſign was not, to provoke and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate; but, if he could, to win, and prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Non-juring Brethren with Calmneſs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedneſs; to examine candidly, whether what he had writ, was the Senſe of that Learned Convocation, or no? Hoping that if they found it was, they might be brought over to comply with, and increaſe the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of this Preſent Government. Far, therefore, was he from reproaching them with <hi>Malice</hi> or <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance;</hi> for he Reverenced the Perſons, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired the Parts, and lamented the loſs of many of them. So that the Truth is, thoſe words never fell from the Pen of the Author; and therefore he deſires
<pb facs="tcp:105902:3"/>that the <hi>Diſſembling Stationer,</hi> who abuſed him in Printing the Book without his knowledg, may be examined about it; for till thoſe words were Printed, he knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them. Whoever, therefore would be ſo abuſed, may commit his Papers to Mr. <hi>C</hi> —, and from his Confederacy with the Non-Jurors Party, he may expect to be ſo treated.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105902:3"/>
            <head>THE VINDICATION OF OBEDIENCE TO THE Preſent Government, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Concerning the Imputation caſt on thoſe who took the Oaths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Publication of the Convocation-Book.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE firſt Effort of the Anſwerer, is an Imputation of Guilt upon all the Jurors, and that, <hi>whether the Allegations of the Author from the Convocation</hi> (p. 1.) <hi>be true or falſe.</hi> This is hard on many a good man, that knew nothing, either of the obſcure Convocation, or the obſcurer Author: But ſo it is, <hi>For this can by no means juſtifie them, being at the beſt, but a Pretence taken up after the Fact; and as a ſubſequent Law cannot condemn, ſo neither can it juſtifie a Fact previous to it.</hi> But doth he think the Author produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this for a Reaſon of what he had beforehand done? The Anſwerer is not ſo ſoft, but he knew this to be only an Inducement to ſuch as himſelf, that were more ſcrupulous of the Equity and Legality of it. And the Caſe is this,</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> had not by any Publick Act, that we knew of, interpoſed her Judgment on either ſide, but every man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105902:4"/>was left to the Direction of his own Conſcience, guided by the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Principles of that Church, and the Word of God: And all the Obligation that the Church could lay upon them, was only an acting conſonantly to her declared Principles. Hereupon ſome took the Oaths, and ſome did not: and yet I dare not think but that both Parties acted on a Principle of Conſcience. Afterwards an old Convocation-Book is produced, and the Jurors peruſing it, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to juſtify their Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Now though the ſubſequent Diſcovery could not be produced, as the Ground and Reaſon of their Previous Act; yet, ſure I am, it doth clear and vindicate them from that <hi>Scandal,</hi> of their deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Old Principles, which ſome men labour to caſt upon them: And that was all that was deſigned from it.</p>
               <p>But if in the Innocency of our Souls we had acted beſides the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which were not ſufficiently declared to us; could thoſe who kept this Book ſo long private, and afterwards publiſh'd it, as if it had been meant for a Snare to our Conſciences, hold themſelves excuſed? Whatever they can do in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> we are call'd upon to <hi>ſhew any other Publick Act of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>any Opinion of one of the approved Sons thereof, the practice of any one that own'd her Principles, in favour of the Doctrines we now teach, and the Practices we now follow, and then we</hi> ſhall be allowed to <hi>ſay ſomething.</hi> To obtain his favour, though the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples whereupon men took the Oaths, were various, yet I will inſtance ſome of them, and oblige my Anſwerer, by confirming them both by the Authority of Principles and Practice; which is all that a Man can require. Now,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some men took the Oaths upon a Suppoſition, That the Violation of the Fundamental Laws of the Land, did releaſe them from the Duty of their Allegiance: and though the Convocation-Book doth no where purpoſely diſcourſe this Caſe,
<note place="margin">P. 27.</note> yet the Notion that it gives of Tyranny (of which more preſently) and its vindicating the <hi>Jews</hi> in oppoſing <hi>Autiochus Epiphanes,</hi> a Tyrant, leaves us ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doubtful of their ſenſe herein. But tho they be ſilent, ſince the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-man, that is a Man approved, will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the Anſwerer, he ſhall have Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi>'s Judgment in this Caſe, who diſcourſing purpoſely of Chriſtian Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">P. 279. Ed. 1586.</note> 
                  <hi>Dare not raſhly pronounce all that reſiſt, to be Rebels; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Caſes may ſo fall out, even in Chriſtian Kingdoms, where the People may plead their Right againſt their Prince, and not be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with Rebellion.</hi> And being demanded to produce an Example, he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105902:4"/>adds, <hi>If a Prince ſhould go about to ſubject his Kingdom to a Foreign Realm; or Change the Form of the Commonwealth from Impery to Tyranny; or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Laws eſtabliſhed by Common Conſent of Prince and People, to execute his own pleaſure; in theſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and other Caſes, which might be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if the Nobles and Commons joyn together to defend their Ancient and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Liberty, Regiment and Law, they may not well be counted Rebels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This will juſtifie, I think, all thoſe that deſerted his Late Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, had they done more than they did. For an Embaſſy to <hi>Rome,</hi> an Arbitrarineſs over Laws, and before the Oaths were impoſed, (yea, probably before the Deſertion) an Open Negotiation with <hi>France,</hi> which means our Slavery; amounts to ſuch a Vindication of us and them, as cannot from this Principle be denied.</p>
               <p>And this his Determination is not deſtitute of all Reaſon: For if our Allegiance reſpect primarily the Government, and then the Governour, as the Head of it,
<note place="margin">See his Caſe of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</note> as Biſhop <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> ſeems to intimate; it ſollows thence, That by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Duty that we owe unto the Government, Allegiance muſt (although the Rightful Governour by withdrawing, incapacitate himſelf to receive it) be paid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where or other, or elſe the Government muſt be diſſolved. And ſince this Learned Biſhop judged thus, I doubt not, but as ſome others that built on the ſame Principles, he would have practiſed ſo alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others ſuppoſing that the King's Deſertion, or Abdication, (which you will) left them in a State of Liberty, thought their late Oath of Allegiance to him was vacated, and ſo were free to oblige themſelves anew. And my Lord <hi>Clarendon,</hi> obſerving that the Word <hi>Abdicate</hi> is no <hi>new Word;</hi> nor the Caprice and Humour of Princes <hi>to abdicate their Kingdoms,</hi> a new thing: And repreſenting it as <hi>the hardeſt Caſe of Subjects, without their Privity,
<note place="margin">Surv. of <hi>Lev.</hi> p. 94, 95.</note> to be left in an inſtant, without any Protection, without any Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as a Prey to all that are too ſtrong for them.</hi> He adds, <hi>That it is no New Tranſaction for Kings and Princes to reſign and RELINQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ISH THEIR CROWN AND SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREIGNTY; nor may it be the better for being old.</hi> Yet beſides other Accounts there mentioned; <hi>Some Princes,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>have been ſo H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MORO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, as upon the FROWARDNESS AND RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FRACTORINESS OF THEIR S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECTS, AND BECA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SETHEY CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD NOT GOVERNIN THAT MANNER THEY HAD A MIND TO DO, TO AB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICATE THE GOVERNMENT, AND WO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD HAVE BEEN GLAD AFTERWARDS TO HAVE
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105902:5"/>RES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MED IT.</hi> Now, I imagine, according to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Great Stateſman, and true Church-man, that our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to the Late King is void.</p>
               <p>And the Letter (of which I have ſufficient Teſtimony) ſent from the Jeſuits to King <hi>James,</hi> at <hi>Sailsbury,</hi> adviſing him to leave the Kingdom, with a promiſing Aſſurance, That he ſhould be <hi>Reſtored, and have his ENDS upon us;</hi> implies ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe than a Caprice or Humour.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The moſt that I have had Converſe with, conclude their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties to have a Right to, as well as Poſſeſſion of the Crown; and that not only from the Law of the Land, which receives and owns them as Legal King and Queen; but alſo upon the Appeal which they made to God, for the Injuſtice done them, on account of the Impoſtor; which being determined on their ſides, fairly gives them a Divine Right. And if ſo, then the Ground-work of the Gentleman's whole Anſwer is undermined, and his Building muſt fall. And this the Author in his Pamphet aſſerted; but becauſe he knew not what to ſay to it, he haughtily paſt it by.</p>
               <p>And thus much for the Principles of ſome Approved Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-men.</p>
               <p>Then for their Practice. The Caſe of the Engagement, repreſented by the Judicious Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> who plainly intimates ſome good men to have taken it, and which is left almoſt in an <hi>Aequilibrio</hi> by that profound Caſuiſt; nay, and which was taken by a Great and Good Man (now with God) a Dying Advocate of the Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience, ſhews the Practices of ſome that have owned her Principles, not to be altogethee repugnant to ours. But this is an unpleaſing Subject, becauſe reflexive upon other men. From hence therefore let us proceed to enquire ſomething after the Convocation-Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>An Account of the Convocation-Book, and why it wanted the Royal Confirmation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Senſe and meaning of this Convocation being to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after, eſpecially in theſe two things, 1. Whether Right muſt of neceſſity be united to Authority, before our Allegiance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105902:5"/>can be due unto it? And 2. When a Revolution of Government may be ſuppoſed to have obtained a thorow Settlement? I thought it not amiſs to enquire into the Reaſons for the calling of the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the circumſtances of Affairs when the Book was written; and the Cauſes why it was laid to ſleep, not being ſuffer'd to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with the Royal Confirmation: For the underſtanding of theſe, will mightily aſſiſt us to comprehend their meaning. And what I have received is thus:</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> growing weary of their wars with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> ſeeing Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the great ſupporter of the <hi>Dutch</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Houſe of <hi>Auflria,</hi> to grow old, and knowing that <hi>James,</hi> then King of the <hi>Scots,</hi> was, after her deceaſe, to ſucceed her in the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> a Prince of a Peaceable Diſpoſition; they made previous Applications to him, to pre-engage him, when he came to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> to mediate a Truce, or Peace, between them and <hi>Holland.</hi> The good Queen, according to the courſe of Nature, in ſome time after dies; whereupon the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by their Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, as ſoon almoſt as King <hi>James</hi> was ſeated on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, renew their Negotiation with him, to mediate the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Truce; ſuppoſing the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Provinces</hi> would ſcarce refuſe his Interpoſition, becauſe at that time he held in his hands ſome Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary Towns of theirs, which had been delivered to the late Queen. The King being of himſelf inclinable to Peace, and to oblige the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (who had a Pontifical claim to the Crown of <hi>England</hi>) to own and acknowledg his Right and Title to that Crown, that ſo he might ſecure to himſelf the certainty of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eaſe and ſafety, undertakes the Mediation: But difficulties ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the <hi>Dutch</hi> Pretentions, who demanded to be acknowledged a Free and Independent State, tho' they had but lately withdrawn themſelves from the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> taking this to be a tender Point, and of great conſequence to all Crowned Heads, if a Province or Principality having ſhaken off their Ancient Lord, might ſet up for a Free and Independent State; deſirous alſo to over-rule the <hi>Dutch</hi> in their Allegations to this Claim, on the apprehenſion of a Fear that it would void the overtures of the deſigned Truce: That he might do it with the greater appearance of Authority and Judgment, he reſolves to conſult his Convocation about the Origine of Government, its various Forms, Alterations, and Modifications, intending them eſpecially to exalt the Sacredneſs and Grandeur of Monarchy.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105902:6"/>
               <p> Accordingly the Convocation go to work, and deduce the Power of Government from its natural and prime Original; taking notice what it was in it ſelf; whence Tyranny and Arbitrary Power uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped upon the Patriarchal: How that again was retrenched, and the True Fatherly Government ſetled amongſt his own People the <hi>Jews,</hi> till the Captivity of <hi>Babylon;</hi> giving alſo an Account what became of them afterwards, what Revolutions they underwent, till they, and all the Weſtern World were made ſubject to the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagle.</p>
               <p>This led them to treat of the Variation of Government by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, who caſts down Kings, and ſets up Kings; who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Kingdoms, and turns them into Ariſtocratical, or Democratical States; and on the contrary, States into Dukedoms, Elective Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, and the like. As alſo what Obedience ought to be paid to the ſaid Governments, when they are once throughly ſetled upon ſuch Revolutions; laying down a Rule, when People with a ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may, nay ought to pay Obedience to their Authority. But their Determination herein touching too hard upon the Claims of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns, and the Royalties of Monarchies (of which ſcarce ever Prince had more tender feeling, than that his Majeſty of <hi>Britain</hi>) King <hi>James</hi> is diſpleaſed with it, and them; charging them, that they had dipped too deep into what all Princes did reſerve amongſt the <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> as from his Letter at the end may be ſeen: and by Orders ſent by Mr. Sollicitor, reſtrains them from medling any farther in it. And this, I believe, might be a Reaſon, why the Convocation, which had promiſed to treat of the Government of the whole World, did not handle more particularly the Caſe of Free and Independent States, which are, and were, one ſort of Government in the World, and comprized by them (as I before hinted) in the word King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; and which the clew of their diſcourſe would have led them to; and they plainly ſeem to aim at, <hi>Ch. &amp; Ca.</hi> 23. had they not by a Prohibition from the King been reſtrained.</p>
               <p>However, they ſaid enough to maintain the <hi>Dutch</hi> Pretences, who inſiſted immovably on the Claim of being acknowledged a Free, and Independent State; or elſe no Accommodation would be hearkened to, no Truce concluded. And the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Affairs being ſuch, at that time, as would not ſuffer them to conteſt the matter any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, they thought it convenient to yield to their Claim (or if you would have it in the Anſwerer's Language, to transfer their Right over to the States) whereupon a Truce betwixt them was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whereof King <hi>James</hi> was made the Chief Guarantee. And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105902:6"/>theſe were the Circumſtances when the Convocation ſat, as from the Hiſtory of thoſe Times, the Date of the Convocation, which was called <hi>Anno</hi> 1603, and continued by Adjournments and Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, to 1610. that is, a year after the aforeſaid Truce was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, which commenced in <hi>April, Anno</hi> 1609. and ended after the Term of Twelve years; and above all, by King <hi>James</hi> his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to this Convocation, if we could be ſo happy as to get a fight of it.</p>
               <p>Thus the Affairs of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> were Accommodated; but it netled King <hi>James,</hi> to have the Convocation determine ſo poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively of Obedience to be due to Governments eſtabliſhed upon ſuch Revolutions as are there mentioned. Hereupon it is ſuppoſed that he refuſed the Canons his Royal Aſſent, and left them to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured <hi>Blattis &amp; Tineis,</hi> or at leaſt by Old Time, if by nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>But for the Honour of the Convocation, ſomething was to appear, leſt that Venerable Aſſembly ſhould ſeem to meet only as the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror with his Army, to gather Cockle-ſhels; And therefore, as I gueſs (for it is no more) the Book, call'd <hi>God and the King,</hi> (which whoever compares with this, will find in many things of its laſt Part, to be an Abſtract of ſome of theſe Chapters) was collected hence, and ſent abroad into the World to atone his diſpleaſed Majeſty. And ſo much for the Convocation, and the Occaſion of their being ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, and Commiſſionated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Concerning the Four Propoſitions of Government; Extracted out of the Convocation-Book.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Grievous Charge is now laid againſt me, That though I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to demonſtrate, yet I have <hi>omitted many things that are material,
<note place="margin">P. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> and pertinent to the preſent Controverſie about Government and Allegiance. That what I have drawn up into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſitions, I have in ſome of them (if not in all) curtail'd and diminiſhed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll ſenſe of the Convocation. That, above all, by adding words and Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Gloſſes, and Explications, I have deſtroyed the Text, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tly corrupted, and perverted their ſenſe.</hi> Well! I will not take any exceptions at his words, elſe how I could argue on a Subject, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105902:7"/>adding Gloſſes and Explications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I know not; but how far I am guilty, I leave the Reader to judge, and ſo haſten to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. The Firſt of which was,</p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROP. I. <hi>That the Power of Kings was originally Patriarchal, Derived from God, and not from the People,</hi> Ca. 2, 6, 13.</head>
                  <p>On which the Complaint is, That <hi>I have expounded away,
<note place="margin">P. 12.</note> as I always do, the ſenſe of the Convocation;</hi> for, it ſeems, I ſay, that Kings are, and ought to be bound up by Laws;
<note place="margin">P. 13.</note> and <hi>he prays to know by what Laws?</hi> The very next words tell him: but becauſe nothing will digeſt with him but the expreſs words of the Convocation-Book, from them he might have underſtood, that they wre the Laws of God and Nature,
<note place="margin">P. 9, <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.</note> as they did concern Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Societies and Governments, which ſurely ought to bind; But why did not I expreſs it in the words of the Convocation-Book, to which I refer? A man hath need of patience that hath to deal with ſuch a Queſtionariſt. But to give him ſatisfaction. It was becauſe I had a mind to deliver in general what the Convocation had ſaid but in Particular. For that very ſame Reaſon that obliged the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Civil-Laws of their Particular Government, obligeth all other Kings to the obſervation of the Fundamental Eſtabliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Laws of their Reſpective Kingdoms. And ſince it is the King's being bound up by Laws that ſtomachs the Anſwerer, I deſire he would take notice from the Convocation, what thoſe Princes are that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> not be bound up by Law; <hi>For Nimrod,</hi> ſay they, (and by a Parity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Reaſon we may add all ſuch like Princes) <hi>not cententing himſelf with the Patriarchal or Mild Government, ordained of God by the Laws Reaſon and Nature, became a Tyrant, and Lord of Confuſion</hi> Should have delivered this Notion of Tyranny, to be ſure we had had it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his Scheme of New Notions; and therefore I recommend it to the Anſwerers conſideration: Only I obſerve from them, That a Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Power, and the being limited in the Exerciſe of Power by Law are not inconſiſtent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105902:7"/>
                  <head>PROP. II. <hi>That Deſcent in Hereditary Kingdoms, is the Ordinary way whereby a Right and Title to the Crown is claimable.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>His Quarrel here is, that theſe Words, <hi>The Ordinary Way,</hi> are Words of mine own; for he obſerves that I add,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>I ſay, the ordinary Way:</hi> And ſince theſe were Words of mine own, how could I let him know it otherwiſe, than by telling him, and all men, that they were <hi>my Saying.</hi> Surely the Cauſe is ſinking, when men catch thus at Reeds and Ruſhes. But ſince I muſt not <hi>ſay,</hi> pray do you ſay: Is the Propoſition true or falſe? If true, why ſo captious at it? and if falſe, why do you not reject it? No matter for that, for <hi>tho' there be ſome extraordinary ways in Hereditary Kingdoms,
<note place="margin">P. 2, 3.</note> that may give a Right and Title to the Crown beſides Deſcent; yet the Author's extraordinary way is none of them.</hi> For this I ſhall appeal to the Reader to judge; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for his ingenuity in interpreting the Author's Meaning from the Convocation-Book, which aſſerts, <hi>That the Lord both may, and is able to overthrow Kings or Emperors, notwithſtanding any Claim, Right, Title or Intereſt, which they can challenge to their Countries, Kingdoms, or Empires,</hi> to be only God's <hi>Permiſſive Providence,</hi> which, I think, the Author ſcarce mentions above once, and that far from the Senſe that the Anſwerer would inſinuate. But my Citation and his muſt be adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted anon, and therefore here I will ſpeak no more of this matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROP. III. <hi>That no Violence is to be uſed to Kings from their own Subjects, for any Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities that they commit.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>doth not fully expreſs the ſenſe of the Convocation;</hi> yet he intimates not wherein it is defective; <hi>but the Author's Comment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys it.</hi> How does this appear? Why, Becauſe the Doctrines of Paſſive Obedience to a Government eſtabliſhed by Law, whether the Prince be Limited or Abſolute, is of abſolute Neceſſity to the ſupport of the Government. And is it not ſo? <hi>But this is Mr.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 3.</note> Johnſon<hi>'s Paſſive Obedience, that is limited to the Laws, and not to the Prince.</hi> The Author troubles not himſelf in thinking what it is, but ſhrewdly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105902:8"/>that the Anſwerer was conſcious to himſelf that he abuſed him, when in the very next Words he confeſſes, that <hi>if ſo, this is not only a plain Contradiction to the Convocations, but to his own extracted Propoſition.</hi> Whence the Author ſuppoſes, that his Suppoſitive <hi>If,</hi> argues too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly a conſcientiouſneſs of Guilt.</p>
                  <p>Before I paſs hence, I muſt take notice of a fine Word that the Anſwerer hath met with, <hi>Yclepd Irregularity,</hi> which again he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Author can mean <hi>nothing leſs by, than a Prince's act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and governing againſt Law:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 3.</note> by his favour, <hi>beſides Law,</hi> will amount to an irregularity; and for his new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Univerſal <hi>Any,</hi> when the Logicians ſhall ſo eſteem it, I will retrench my Indefinites.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROP. IV. <hi>That having ſworn Allegiance to a Prince, we cannot without the dreadful guilt of Perjury, transfer our Allegiance, whilſt he continues to have an Authoritative Right and Title to the Crown.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Kindly here he corrects the falſe Impreſſion, C. 36. which ſhould have been the 30.</p>
                  <p>But what moſt grieves him here are, the Cramp-words of <hi>an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative Right and Title,</hi> and not finding them in the Convocation-Book, he diſcovers again, that I confeſs them my own, in that <hi>I ſay, an Authoritative Right and Title;</hi> but <hi>he deſires the favour once more to know where I had them.</hi> I am loth to diſoblige him, and therefore may he know, that I had them from the Words of <hi>Can.</hi> 31. where the Authority of <hi>Alexander</hi> is acknowledged to be ſetled amongſt the <hi>Jews;</hi> which, if the Story be true (and the Convocation-Book, not I, am to anſwer for that) of neceſſity muſt be in the Life-time of <hi>Darius,</hi> as the Book plainly intimates, <hi>Ca.</hi> &amp; <hi>Can.</hi> 30 &amp; 31. taking notice, that he had preſerved his Life by flight; and if ſo, there was an Expiration, though not of <hi>Darius</hi>'s Life, yet of his Authoritative Right and Title.</p>
                  <p>And this the Anſwerer fairly confeſſeth in theſe Words. <hi>The Convocation ſuppoſes that</hi> Darius <hi>had not at that time that Authoritative Title the Author mentions; for they tell us expreſly, that this was when</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius <hi>was eſcaped by flight,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 27.</note> after his Army was diſcomfited.</hi> And ſo both he and they confeſs him at this time to be <hi>Alive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105902:8"/>
                  <p> But ſaith he, <hi>The Author goes on</hi> (and on he may go, for any ſtop that he hath given him) <hi>aſſerting, that the</hi> Claim of Right <hi>without the Authority, cannot Challenge our Allegiance.</hi> Which, whether the Senſe of the Convocation, or no, is now to be examin'd.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>
                     <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> Whether in the Senſe of the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to be always joyn'd as the Foundation of our Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ONE of the greateſt Points in Controverſy, between the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and the Anſwerer, is conconcering Right and Authority; and whether they muſt of neceſſity be united, before a Foundation, whereon to build our Allegiance, can be laid; and therefore to place this in the cleareſt Light, I will
<list>
                     <item>I. Conſider what is meant by Right and Authority.</item>
                     <item>II. Lay down the Grounds on which each Party builds their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the Convocation favouring them.</item>
                     <item>III. Impartially, and in their own words, ſtate the matter in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate betwixt them. And.</item>
                     <item>IV. Fairly adjuſt the Authority that each Party brings from the Convocation, that the unbiaſt Reader may ſee where the Truth lies. Now.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. For the word <hi>Right,</hi> when it is ſeparated from, and oppoſed to <hi>Authority,</hi> the Author always underſtands a Right or Title found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Proximity of Blood, which the Anſwerer calls a Legal Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: I ſuppoſe he means it of the Law of Nature, which indeed doth reſpect the aforeſaid Right of Proximity of Blood. Otherwiſe, if he means it of the Laws of the Land, it is very plain, whatever Nature may, our Conſtitution is not ſuch, as of neceſſity annexeth the Crown to the next Heir of the Blood; for to ſay, that the King and Parliament cannot diſpoſe of it otherwiſe, is a <hi>Praemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire.</hi> And it was actually diſpoſed of otherwiſe in its deſcent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> or Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> one of them being what I will not Name. A King <hi>de facto</hi> too, is a Legal King, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105902:9"/>to the Laws of the Realm. Yet, our Anſwerer, I believe in his Senſe will not own him ſuch; ſo that by Right, he means the Right of Nature, or Proximity of Blood, which is what the Author underſtood by it, when he oppoſed it to Authority, nor could he indeed underſtand by it any thing elſe; for <hi>Authority</hi> in this Caſe is nothing elſe, but that Divine Power, which God, who is Superior to all Laws, intruſts a Perſon with from above, to act and execute with Equity and Mercy, the Adminiſtration of a Government committed to his Hands. So that the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition betwixt <hi>Right and Authority,</hi> in the Author's Senſe, and he thinks in the Convocation too, (of which anon) is not as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer ſuppoſeth betwixt <hi>Right, i. e.</hi> a Legal Title and <hi>Poſſeſſion;</hi> (which he pretends is all that the Author means by <hi>Authority;</hi> but the Author, if he will give him Liberty to explain himſelf, means ſomething more by it, as is above expreſſed); But plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Oppoſition is betwixt <hi>Right,</hi> as that implies a Civil Title amongſt Men, which excludes the Pretences of all other Humane <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> as that includes in it a Claim from God. Theſe two generally are united; but God for Cauſes beſt known to himſelf, may, and ſometimes doth ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them; and when they are thus ſeparated, ſince it is by him that Kings Reign, the Author ſuppoſeth his Allegiance to be due to God's Authority, and not to the Civil Right: And he thought he had proved this from the Inſtance of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> who being led Captive into <hi>Babylon,</hi> though they ſurvived there, could lay no claim to the Allegiance of their Subjects. And this it is, or nothing, that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer muſt oppoſe. But he Equivocates in his Notion of <hi>Right,</hi> and ſometimes underſtands by it <hi>Civil Right,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Divine;</hi> and on this Homonimy the whole Stream of his Anſwer runs. He muſt underſtand by it <hi>Civil Right,</hi> when he puts the Query,
<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether Allegiance may be ſeparated from Right, and transferred to Authority without Right?</hi> So, when he affirms, that according to the Convocation, <hi>Right without Authority may,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and ought to challenge Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and that Authority without Right cannot challenge it.</hi> Where, if he do not mean a <hi>Civil Right,</hi> he fights without an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary. But then, in the very next Page, by <hi>Right,</hi> he muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Divine Right;</hi> where in the caſe of <hi>Jehu</hi> and <hi>Ahud,</hi> he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Page 5.</note> 
                  <hi>It is plain from the Convocation-Book, that they had a Right before Allegiance became due.</hi> Where by <hi>Right</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105902:9"/>he muſt underſtand <hi>Divine Right,</hi> for they had no <hi>Civil Right,</hi> or Legal Claim to the Crown; for <hi>Joram</hi> being in Poſſeſſion and the other out, his Title was far better by all Humane Laws: And as for <hi>Ahud,</hi> his being acknowledged a Subject, he could pretend no Legal Title to the Crown. Nor can he evade this, by ſaying, that they had both Gods expreſs Nomination, for that cannot alter the nature of things, and create them a Civil Legal Title, altho it gives them a Divine Authority, which is far Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior unto it. 'Tis true, he affirms that the <hi>Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion expreſly aſſerts</hi> Jehu <hi>to be a Lawful King;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 5.</note> but I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect he ſhould recall his words, unleſs he can make a Note of Similitude, <hi>As,</hi> of neceſſity to be a Character of Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, and prove things that may be conſtrued only to be alike or equal, to be the very ſame; for the words are, <hi>That</hi> Jehu, <hi>upon the knowledge of Gods will,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>page</hi> 46.</note> and the Submiſſion of the Princes, and Captains of</hi> Iſrael <hi>unto hsm,</hi> As to their Lawful King, <hi>did put in execution the ſaid Meſſage by killing</hi> Joram. Where the words only expreſs the fullneſs of the Submiſſion of the Captains to him; who ſubmitted as intirely <hi>As to their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King,</hi> but need not at all to reſpect a Legal Title for he had none. Thus the Author hath declared what he means by <hi>Right and Authority,</hi> and doubts not but to manifeſt it in its due place, to be the meaning of the Convocation too. For,</p>
               <p>Secondly, The account that he hath given of the calling of this Convocation, and the Circumſtances of Affairs that during its continuance occur'd; (which was to conſider of the Claim of the United Provinces, as to their being a Free and Independent State,) doth very plainly Evidence it. For ſince their Authority could have no Legal Foundation, it muſt wholly be derived from a Divine Interpoſition; and it was not Civil Right, but Gods Providence and Pleaſure that poſſeſſed them of the Powers of Government. I know the Anſwerer pretends, <hi>the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Paſſive Obedience and Non-reſiſtance to be the whole Deſign of the Book.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 21.</note> Now all that I ſhall ſay to this at preſent is, that neither of theſe is ſo much as once expreſly named in all the Book, and that this is the <hi>whole deſign of it,</hi> will be found difficult for him to prove. But upon the apprehenſion of theſe different Ends and Intention of the Convocation, the different Conſtruction of the words of the Book, are in ſome meaſure grounded, therefore as I promiſed,</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105902:10"/>
               <p> Thirdly, I muſt impartially, and in their own words ſtate the Matter in Debate betwixt them. And the Author plainly affirms, that <hi>Right and Authority may be ſeparated, and that when they are ſo ſeparated,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>page</hi> 5.</note> the Claim of Right,</hi> i. e. <hi>Civil Right, without the Authority,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Divine Power of Government, cannot challenge our Allegiance.</hi> On the other ſide the Anſwerer aſſerts, <hi>that Right without Authority may,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>page</hi> 4.</note> and ought to challenge our Allegiance; and that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority without Right cannot challenge it.</hi> Now if Reaſon might decide it, ſince the Authority even in Civil Right comes from God, <hi>and the Powers that be are ordained of God,</hi> it ſeems ſtrange, that the Ordinance of God cannot command our Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, becauſe it doth not quadrate with the Conſtitution of Man: or that God who is acknowledged by the Anſwerer to be above all Laws, cannot by his Providence diſpoſe of his own Power, but according to Law. But I muſt remember, that our Appeal was to be to the Convocation book, and to it therefore let us go; which is the laſt thing.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, To adjuſt the Authority that each Party brings from the Convocation-book, that the Unprejudiced Reader may ſee on which ſide the plain Truth doth lye, I will begin with the Author, whoſe Aſſertion is, <hi>That the Claim of Right without Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, is not ſufficient to challenge our Allegiance;</hi> the terms of which being before explained. he produceth theſe Authorities from the Convocation-book to confirm it; which if a Man will but open his Eyes, are poſitive and determinative: The Ground on which the Convocation builds, the Juſtification of <hi>Jehu,</hi> and <hi>Ahad,</hi> in laying violent hands on their lawful Sovereigns clearly prove it, for that is this, that God <hi>may, and is able to overthrow any Kings or Emperors,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>page</hi> 53.</note> notwithſtanding any Claim, Right, Title or Intereſt, which they can challenge to their Countries, Kingdoms or Empires.</hi> So that here is an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to which the Captains did pay Allegiance, as to their <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King</hi> acknowledged without Right, and executed without Guilt. To put this paſt all doubt, the Convocation-book having told us, that <hi>it was not lawful for any Perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
<note place="margin">ibid.</note> upon pretence of any Revelation, Inſpiration or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment from the Divine Majeſty, either to touch the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Sovereign, or to bear Arms againſt him;</hi> makes this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, <hi>Except God ſhould firſt advance the ſaid Perſon from his private Eſtate, and make him a King or an Abſolute Prince, to ſucceed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105902:10"/>his late Maſter in his Kingdom or Principality.</hi> Which words if they were not intended to expreſs a Separation of <hi>Authority from Right,</hi> and when they are ſo ſeparated, to vindicate our Allegiance to the Perſon, whom God from a private Eſtate advanceth to be King, have no deſign or meaning at All. It is to no purpoſe for the Anſwerer to pretend here Gods expreſs Nomination; for that is only to ſay that God may do by Revelation, what he cannot by Providence; and the one ought to be obeyed, and not the other, whereas if it be Gods doing in either way, it requires our Submiſſion.</p>
               <p>Again, the Convocation book expreſly teacheth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <hi>That Authority, tho unjuſtly gotten, and wrung by force from the True and Lawful Poſſeſſor (who ſurely had, and is here ſuppoſed to have the Legal Right) being always Gods Authority, is ever when any ſuch Alterations are throughly ſettled, to be Reverenced and Obeyed by all ſorts of People, and that for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Where if they do not diſtinguiſh <hi>Authority from Right,</hi> and require our Obedience to Authority againſt Right, no words can declare it.</p>
               <p>Again, ſpeaking of ſuch Governments as are founded on (being <hi>begun</hi>) <hi>by Rebellion</hi> (and I hope the Anſwerer will not ſay that Rebellion hath Right on its ſide) the Convocation owns <hi>them, when throughly ſettled,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>page</hi> 59.</note> to have Gods Authority, and that the People who live within the Territories of ſuch new Governments, are bound to be ſubject to Gods Authority.</hi> If this be not Demonſtration, I will pretend no more to it; for it is hence plain enough, that the Claim of Right without Authority, cannot challenge our Allegiance, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The Caſe of the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Ammonites</hi> who had thus Authority over the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Hiſtory of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles,</hi> and the very frame of the Governments in being throughout all the World, are ſo many Inſtances of this Truth.</p>
               <p>What the Anſwerer affirms to be the meaning of the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation-book, is this, that <hi>Right without Authority, may and ought to challenge our Allegiance,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>page</hi> 4.</note> and that Authority without Right cannot challenge it.</hi> Now all that he brings for proof of this, are theſe words,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>If any Man ſhall affirm that the Kingdom of</hi> Judah, <hi>by Gods Ordinance going by Succeſſion, when one King was Dead, his Heir was not in Right their King,</hi> (<hi>howbeit by ſome</hi> Athaliah <hi>he might be hindered from enjoying it</hi>) <hi>or that the People were not bound without any farther Circumſtance, upon ſufficient notice of their former Kings death, to have obeyed his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105902:11"/>Heir apparent, as their lawful King, he doth greatly err.</hi> Add the Inſtance of <hi>Joaſh</hi> and <hi>Athaliah, Where notwithſtanding</hi> Joaſh <hi>had none of our Authors Authoritative Right and Title,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ch. &amp; Can.</hi> 23. <hi>page</hi> 4.</note> (as the Anſwerer ſaith, but if you believe it, you believe a notorious Untruth, as will ſhortly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear) <hi>and had only the Claim of Right, without the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, yet when</hi> Jehojada <hi>called the People together, and acquainted them with the Preſervation of the Prince, they altogether by a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant acknowledged their Allegiance to him, as to their Lawful King, and in conſequence of that ſlew</hi> Athaliah <hi>the Uſurper.</hi> This is the whole of his Pretences, and all that he can make of it is, That God having declared that he would not give his Authority to any Perſon to Sway the Scepter of <hi>Judah,</hi> but only ſuch as were of the Line of <hi>David;</hi> whoever did aſcend the Throne, not being of that Stock and Lineage, did Uſurp upon Gods Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And when he can produce ſuch a Declaration of Gods Pleaſure concerning all other Kingdoms, the Kingdoms of the whole World, (of which in General the Convocation treats) then, and not till then, we ſhall allow his Plea; for ſurely a particular and exempt priviledged Caſe of the Kingdom of <hi>Judah,</hi> will not be a ſtanding Rule for the Kingdoms of the whole World.</p>
               <div type="case_study">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Caſe of</hi> Athaliah.</head>
                  <p>But becauſe this is all that he can build on, it ſhall have a particular Diſquiſition. The Caſe of <hi>Athaliah</hi> is the Burden of the Song, let us therefore examine the Convocation-book about it, which repreſents it thus.</p>
                  <p>David <hi>was called and advanced to the Kingdom of</hi> Judah <hi>by God himſelf,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Can.</hi> 14.</note> as truly as</hi> Aaron <hi>was to the Prieſthood; and</hi> Davids <hi>Poſterity had by Gods Ordinance, as rightful an Intereſt to ſucceed him in his ſaid Kingdom,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>See Can.</hi> 17.</note> as either</hi> Aaron<hi>'s Sons had to ſucceed him in the Prieſthood, or</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Joſhua, <hi>oend the reſt of the Judges, (notwithſtanding that God himſelf did chuſe and named them particularly) had in their Governments: Nor had the People then, any more Authority to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> David, <hi>or any of his Poſterity from being their King, than they had to have expelled either</hi> Moſes <hi>or</hi> Joſhua, <hi>or any of the reſt of the Judges whom God by name did appoint to govern them</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:105902:11"/>
                  <p> But <hi>Athaliah,</hi> after the Death of her Son <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> killed all his Children ſave one,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.</note> who was ſecretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed away, and uſurped the Throne, which ſhe held Six years. After which ſpace of time, <hi>Jehojada</hi> acquainting the Fathers of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> that <hi>Joaſh</hi> of the Seed of <hi>David,</hi> to whoſe Poſterity God had expreſly given the Crown; nay, and what was more, <hi>that it was the Lords Will that he ſhould reign over them,</hi> was alive;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>page</hi> 31.</note> they in Obedience to Gods expreſs command, acknowledge their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to him, and advance him to the Throne. <hi>In all which proceſs</hi> (ſaith the Convocation) <hi>nothing was done either by</hi> Jehojada <hi>the High Prieſt,
<note place="margin">ibid.</note> or by the reſt of the Princes and People of</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Benjamin, <hi>which God himſelf did not require at their hands.</hi> And let the Anſwerer produce ſuch an Entail of the Crown upon a Family as this is; let him add to that, Gods expreſs command to Dethrone the Poſſeſſor, as the Convocation here ſaith <hi>Jehojada</hi> and the Princes had to depoſe <hi>Athaliah;</hi> and then he produceth ſomething to the purpoſe. Otherwiſe ſince they attempted not to Dethrone <hi>Athaliah,</hi> (tho another had as Divine a Right to the Crown, as <hi>Moſes</hi> who was named by God) till they were anew acquainted, <hi>that it was the Lords Will, that</hi> Joaſh <hi>ſhould reign over them;</hi> it would almoſt move a forward Man to infer the neceſſity of Circumſpection and Caution in the Depoſing even of Uſurpers. However from the Divine Entailment of the Crown of <hi>Judah</hi> on the Poſterity of <hi>David,</hi> it is manifeſt that Authority could not in them be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from Right; and therefore the Anſwerer unjuſtly affirms, <hi>That</hi> Joaſh <hi>had not that Authoritative Right and Title which the Author ſpeaks of;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>page</hi> 4.</note> but only a Claim of Right without Authority,</hi> the contrary to which from what I have ſaid is very evident.</p>
                  <p>What I would obſerve from the caſe of <hi>Joaſh</hi> and <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> is thus. God by expreſs Revelation had given to <hi>David</hi> and his Poſterity the Throne of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and no one of thoſe Kingdoms, without oppoſing the Expreſs Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God, could deny Allegiance to <hi>David</hi> or his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; till he had a Command as expreſſive to withdraw it, as at firſt he had to yield it, <hi>i. e.</hi> a plain Revelation to the contrary. For ſince it was Gods expreſs word to ſettle thoſe Crowns on <hi>David</hi> and his Poſterity, nothing but the ſame word as Expreſſive, could revoke the Donation. It was therefore this expreſs word
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105902:12"/>by his Prophet, revoking (for the Sins of his Poſterity) that grant to <hi>David,</hi> that excuſed the Ten Tribes, in refuſing their Allegiance to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and transferring it to his Competitor: And I believe it was the Admonition of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> from God, requiring the Jews to pay Obedience to <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> that did diſcharge them of their Obedience to the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>David.</hi> For the Anſwerer may pleaſe himſelf with his Conceit of a Transferring Right: But ſure I am, that God having once by Prophecy declared his Entailing the Crown on <hi>David</hi> and his Poſterity; nothing but a Prophecy to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as expreſs as that, could ever revoke it, or vindicate them in paying it elſewhere.</p>
                  <p>What I have diſcourſed of Gods expreſs Nomination of the Poſterity of <hi>David</hi> to rule the Houſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> that it required a Revelation as expreſs to revoke that Authority and Donation; may I think be happily applied unto all other caſes, where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Perſonal Deſignation by Prophecy, the ſpecial Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Providence exalts Perſons and Families unto Thrones, and accordingly Dethrones them. For what Prophecy was to them, both to advance and remove; that Providence muſt be to us. There is now no Perſon, or Family, raiſed to a Crown, but by the Providence of God, and ſince it is Providence alone that doth inaugurate them, when the ſame Providence doth Depoſe them; who are we that we ſhould Fight againſt God? We have, when once the Prevailing Power doth come unto a Settlement, the ſame Providence that acted in their Exaltation and Depreſſion, to direct us in our Duty of Allegiance; even as the Jews of old, had the ſame Spirit of Prophecy to direct them. And ſince it is Providence alone, that by exalting a Perſon or Family to a Crown, gives them a Right unto their Subjects Allegiance: I do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, but when the ſame Providence Remands the Power out of their Hands, and transfers it to ſome other Perſon, or Family, our Allegiance is transferred alſo: for the Power being tranſplanted, our Homage muſt remove with it, or elſe we muſt deny Obedience to that Divine Power which makes Kings, and coming from God is to be reverenced, honored, and obeyed, where ever it pleaſeth him to place it. This I take to be a better account of the Reaſons of our Allegiance being trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrable from one Perſon to another, then his new vamped Notion of transferring a Right, which next comes to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105902:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Concerning a Prince his transferring a Right.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Anſwerer ſaw, and had not the hardineſs to deny that <hi>there were ſome Inſtances of transferring Allegiance men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and juſtified in the Convocation-Book;</hi> and ſince he could not deny them, his Buſineſs is to palliate them.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 4, 5.</note> Hereupon he ſtarts a new, but no ſound Notion of transferring a Right, and diſhoneſtly Fathers it on the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, for he ſaith in theſe Caſes <hi>i. e.</hi> of Revolutions, <hi>the Convocation never requires nor juſtifies the transferring Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, but only where the Right is transferred likewiſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 5.</note> To prove which he unluckily Inſtances in the Caſes of <hi>Jehu</hi> and <hi>Ahud.</hi> But good Mr. <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſpeak out; did <hi>Joram</hi> transfer a Right to <hi>Jehu,</hi> to kill his Perſon and wear his Crown? Did <hi>Eglon</hi> transfer a Right to <hi>Ahud</hi> to ſheath his Dagger in his Belly? Yet <hi>the ſame,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>may be ſaid of the</hi> Jews <hi>Submiſſion and Obedience to the</hi> Babylonians <hi>&amp;c. all mentioned in the Convocation-Book.</hi> If ſo,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 5.</note> I am ſure it is ſuch a transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Right, as Mortals were never in the leaſt acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, till the Anſwerer from Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> was pleaſed to reveal it. And let him here take notice once more, that, <hi>I ſay,</hi> from Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> for he was the firſt that ever I heard of that ſtarted the Notion of a transferring of Sovereignty. So that what the Anſwerer would fix upon the Convocation, is indeed down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Hobbiſm,</hi> and borrowed from the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> where a Power is given to his Soveraign,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 114.</note> to renounce and transfer the Sovereignty to another.</p>
               <p>However on <hi>Jehu</hi> like he drives, and will <hi>have the reſpective Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the</hi> Babylonians, Perſians, &amp;c. <hi>to have a right of Government over the</hi> Jews, <hi>though not in the ſame manner with the former by God's expreſs Nomination, yet a Right they acquired by the Submiſſion and Acknowledgment of thoſe in whom the Right was.</hi> This he ſaith and requires you to believe it, for he never offers to prove it, but from the Author, who expreſly tells you, <hi>That the Kings of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah <hi>became not only Tributary, but Subjects to the King of</hi> Babylon. What! by transferring their Right? Not a word of that; yet that was the thing to be proved. But is not this Gentleman happy in his Proof, and full of them too,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105902:13"/>that is forced to borrow from his Adverſary Teſtimonies to his own ruin. But they <hi>ſubmitted</hi> he ſaith, how I pray? Why! they were conquered, and is not this a pretty way of transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Right.</p>
               <p>I expected he would have produced ſome Inſtrument of a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary transferring their Right, but it all dwindles into Force and Power, and they are conſtrained to part with it, becauſe they cannot keep it. If this be what he means by transferring Right, King <hi>James</hi> his Deſertion transferred it as much as their Submiſſion. Nay, and ſince Ceſſion is one way that he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thus transferring a Right, ſure I am, that the Ceſſion of King <hi>James</hi> which had ſomething of Choice and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarineſs in it being a mixt Action,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 19.</note> implies more of his own Will and Freedom in that Transferance, than any inſtance he hath yet produced. In ſhort, did ever a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror derive the Validity of his Title to his Conqueſts from the conquered Princes transferring his Right? I am ſure of the contrary; and therefore may conclude there was never ſuch a thing as transferring a Right, but only in the Metaphyſical Head of Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> and the Anſwerer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>A Reply to ſome Captious Exceptions of the Anſwerers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE are now come to what the Anſwerer calls the laſt of the Authors firſt Propoſitions, and he may call it an Apple, or an Oyſter, if he pleaſe, (for both are now in Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and) 'tis all one to the Author, who for any thing that Quibbling Anſwerer hath ſaid (after he had given us a caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Wit) meets with him acknowledging it, to lie in this Form That <hi>Government derives its Power from God, and not from the People.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 13.</note> Now though this was not ſo very unlike the firſt Propoſition which was, that, <hi>The Power of King was originally Patriarchal, derived from God, and not from the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> the Predicate being in both the ſame, he might have ſee the Neceſſity of the Author's enlarging the Subject; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105902:13"/>hope by being only more comprehenſive, is not quite another thing. The Convocation undertakes to diſcourſe concerning <hi>the Government of the Kingdoms of the whole World;</hi> by which word Kingdoms, I ſuppoſe they do not ſtrictly mean that one Form of Government, but Synecdochically all other Forms of Government to be underſtood in that, as the chief; hence they treat of <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that I was obliged to enlarge the Terms of my Propoſition to the Proportion of my deſign,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 56.</note> it being to be the Ground work of what was to follow: And tho this perhaps will not content the Captious Anſwerer (who hereupon tells us, <hi>That Government in General is not Patriarchal; neither are other Forms,
<note place="margin">P. 13.</note> beſides Monarchy, Patriarchal;</hi> and more ſuch like Stuff) yet he hopes it may ſatisfie the Candid Reader. But I muſt obſerve his Motions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cannot tell <hi>what is meant by Gods being the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Nature, and conſequently of Humane Societies, but he ſuſpects</hi> ('tis a Jealous Man) ſome bad meaning in it. And if it be as he thinks it is, that Mankind being of a Sociable Nature, by that were directed to Society, and from that, <hi>i. e.</hi> Society, to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, it contradicts the Authors own Propoſition. Now this is only a Spiteful Innuendo, and what a fair Anſwerer would ſcorn to be Guilty of, for he very well knows, that in Nature there is a Priority of Order, when there is none of Time, and the Conſequences of things there, reſpect the manner of our Conceptions, not their Exiſtence; as Light is conceived to be Poſterior to the Sun, whence it comes, tho they both be at one and the ſame Inſtant; even ſo may Society and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be Co-exiſtent, yet one Conſequent to the other in the order of Nature. But the bad meaning is all his own, for the Expreſſion is ſo plain, that none, but who had the deſign of a Scandal, could miſinterpret it; for, what is more Intelligible than this, that Government in General, deriving its Authority from God the Author of Nature, and conſequently of Humane Societies; muſt ſignifie, that the ſame God who was the Author of our Nature being Sociable, was conſequently the Author of Humane Societies, which muſt of neceſſity follow a Sociable Nature. What more ſtrained, forced and diſturbed than his Explication of it is, which firſt would make me ſuppoſe Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies, and then Government, for <hi>they were directed,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to Society, and from that to Government;</hi> as if there could be Society without Government, when Government is only an
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105902:14"/>Adminiſtration of Societies. Such another diſingenious Practice doth he fly to, wherein he pretends that <hi>quoting a Paſſage out of the Convocation book,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 25. <hi>P.</hi> 47.</note> I changed Benedictions into Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, as if they were all one.</hi> Whereas the words were not quoted out of the Convocation-book, but were my own words, put into an Obſervation that I thence had made; ſo that he might have underſtood the word <hi>Benedictions</hi> to have been falſly Printed for <hi>Predictions;</hi> but then he had wanted an Exception againſt the Author; and by ſuch means as theſe muſt a Tottering Cauſe be ſupported.</p>
               <p>The next thing that he is diſpleaſed at, is the Gloſs I give upon theſe words, <hi>That Government is not derived from the People, tho their Conſent be ordinarily neceſſary to the Conſtitution,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 13.</note> both of the Form of Government, and the Perſons Governing.</hi> And is it not ſo?
<note place="margin">ibid.</note> he is ſilent upon it; <hi>But it is plain the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion never thought ſo, but the contrary.</hi> But whence proves he this? not a word of the Pudding; for if you will not believe him, he cannot afford to prove it. But ſure I am, <hi>the Peoples having notice of God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.</note> even his appointing Princes, Judges and Kings, that they might conform themſelves to Obedience, and their chearfully and with great Thankfulneſs ſubmitting themſelves to be ruled by them, their willingly proteſting their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, their following them, their ſhouting when they ſaw them, and ſaying God Save the King, and other ſuch Expreſſions of their Joy and Gladneſs, are no Intimations that their Conſent was not had in all that was done.</hi> Indeed the Canon ſaith, <hi>That the King did not receive any ſuch virtue or ſtrength from the People,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Can.</hi> 17.</note> their ſaid Notice, Preſence and Applauſe, as that without the ſame the ſaid Callings of God, either by Name or by Succeſſion had been Inſufficient.</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>That when God raiſed up Judges to Rule and Govern them,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Can.</hi> 13.</note> the Peoples conſent was not neceſſary thereunto.</hi> But whoever pretended it was when God immediately did Interpoſe; or could ſo much as imagine it? unleſs we ſhould conceive a People ſo Fooliſh as not to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in the manifeſt Choice and Determination of an All-wiſe and an All-good God: or ſo Beſotted, as to think they might inſiſt upon their Right againſt his Declaration, which was the Caſe of <hi>Judah.</hi> And for other the beſt conſtituted Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when the Solemnity of the Coronation is altered, He may then, but not till then, Diſpute the Inſignificancy of their Conſent.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105902:14"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Well at laſt however through all the Authors,</hi> and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerers, <hi>Shufflings and Intermixings, we are got to this Point,
<note place="margin">P. 13.</note> That Government derives its Power from God, and not from the People:</hi> And becauſe I thought that herein we ſhould agree, I made it the Ground-work of the following as well as it is of the antecedent Diſcourſe; and confirmed it (and who would think the Anſwerer ſhould be diſpleaſed, by having ſuch a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Truth confirmed) by three Obſervations; all which are ſo many Arguments, that Government derives its Authority from God. For if all Kingdoms now be in ſome ſort Theocracies; if the Tenure of Sovereigns be ſuch, that God may diveſt them of that Power, and transfer both it, and the Duty that is owing to it, unto ſome other Perſon; it undeniably follows, that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment derives its Power from God. And tho he diſproves not one of theſe, nay fairly acknowledgeth the Truth of the two laſt, yet his Captious Humour will not ſuffer him to paſs over the firſt, becauſe there is ſomething that miſrepreſented, he may find occaſion to talk of. Nothing could be fairer, than having obſerved from the Convocation, that all Kingdoms are now in ſome ſort Theocracies; I ſhould expreſs it in what ſort they were ſo; and this I did, by ſhewing from the Book, <hi>That God uſed the Miniſtry of Civil Magiſtrates,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ch.</hi> 35. <hi>P.</hi> 83.</note> as well in other Countries, as amongſt his own Peculiar People</hi> Iſrael, <hi>without any deſert of theirs, but as in his Heavenly Providence he thought it moſt convenient.</hi> This ſeems to me to reſpect his Choice of the Perſons of the Governours whoſe Miniſtry he uſeth, and ſince this was one Inſtance of the Theocracy of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the Convocation intimates, <hi>when they tell us, that upon recourſe to God, he did appoint one for their Prince,
<note place="margin">P. 18. P. 21.</note> chief Captain, and Ruler.</hi> I think in this ſort and Senſe Chriſt Jeſus, to whom all Power both in Heaven and Earth is committed, doth for the good of his Catholick Church, thus rule the World. And for this Kingdom in particular, it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remarkable, what Mr. <hi>Camden</hi> in his Remains, relates of one <hi>Brithwald</hi> a Monk, who not long before the Conqueſt, buſying his Brain much about the Succeſſion of the Crown, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Royal Blood was almoſt extinguiſhed, had a ſtrange Viſion, and heard a Voice, which forbad him to be Inquiſitive of ſuch Matters, ſounding in his Ears, <hi>The Kingdom of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>is Gods own Kingdom, and for it God himſelf will Provide.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105902:15"/>
               <p> But the Anſwerer doth not much oppoſe this, only he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of a Brood of New Notions, amongſt which Theocracy is one,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 14.</note> and truly as he interprets it to be only <hi>Gods Permiſſive Providence it is ſo:</hi> But then that is a Notion of his own not of the Authors. He next takes notice of the Authors <hi>Infortunity in proving his Principles, who to prove that Providence deſigns the Perſon of the Sovereign in other Kingdoms as well as in</hi> Judah,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>inſtances only in the Kingdom of</hi> Judah.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>And are not theſe Pure Proofs?</hi> But the Author thought he had proved this from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation book, and brought thoſe Inſtances only for an Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the manner how God did it.</p>
               <p>And for the caſe of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> whereon I had remarked, <hi>That God ſometimes for the only deſigned Uſurpation of a Prince, whoſe Title, and that in an Hereditary Kingdom, was altogether indiſputable, does deprive him of the Government in part, or whole, and will not allow him ſo much as to endeavour the regaining of it;</hi> he finds two things that deſerve Reflection; the one is, <hi>That</hi> Rehoboam's <hi>not regaining the Ten Tribes,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 15.</note> was expreſly forbidden by God, and ſo nothing to our Authors purpoſe.</hi> Yes therefore to the Authors purpoſe, becauſe God did forbid it; for this clearly ſhews, that when a Prince is removed for his Uſurpation, it is God that did deprive him; unleſs you will deny the Interpoſition of God in any other way, than expreſs Revelation, which I ſuppoſe you dare not. And this is ſo viſible a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God upon Unjuſt Kings,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Edit. Lat. Lond.</hi> 1651. <hi>P.</hi> 31.</note> that the Book called <hi>God and the King,</hi> cannot but take notice of it, <hi>That it is common, and familiar with God, when he is vehemently provoked by wicked Kings, and the Contemners of his Laws, to threaten them, that he will rent their Kingdoms from them, as he did from</hi> Saul <hi>and</hi> Rehoboam, <hi>and deſtroy and extirpate their Family. But had he not had that expreſs Prohibition, might he not then have endeavoured to regain them?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 15.</note> Yes if he would. <hi>And ſo he did,</hi> but what then? doth God counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Depoſed Uſurpers with Succeſs? No! he never could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his Right: And from this ſomething more would follow than I ſhall mention.</p>
               <p>The other thing, is a foul Prevarication of Scripture, <hi>for the Author ſays, That God deprived</hi> Rehoboam <hi>of his Government, for his only deſigned Uſurpation, whereas the Scripture is as expreſs as can be, that it was for the Idolatry of his Father</hi> Solomon, If ſo, I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105902:15"/>perceive <hi>Rehoboam</hi> had hard meaſure; and God, contrary to his expreſs word, made the <hi>Child to bear the Iniquity of the Father;</hi> which unleſs they imitate the Fathers in Sin, I believe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer will not be ſo hardy as to aſſert; and let him conſider from hence, who makes boldeſt with Scripture. But tell me Sir, was the Cauſe of this Dethronement ſo wholly <hi>Solomons</hi> Idolatry, that <hi>Rehoboam</hi> had no Guilt in it: or if he had Any, ſpeak out, and ſhame the Devil. For you might pretend, if you ſo pleaſed, the Saying which the Lord ſpake by <hi>Ahijah,</hi> when he promiſed <hi>Jeroboam</hi> (to whom he now gave) the Kingdom, to be the cauſe of it, that ſo Gods Word (which the Scripture alſo takes notice of) might be fulfilled. Yet neither of theſe being proper and perſonal to <hi>Rehoboam:</hi> ſome other muſt be produced to clear the Equity of Gods dealing with him. And ſince you diſallow what I have mentioned, pray Sir, turn over your Bible, and Squeeze out any other if you can. Believe me Sir, ſuch Trifling Illuſions as theſe may poſſibly become your Cauſe, but they do not your Coat.</p>
               <p>But the willful Prevarication that follows it is Injurious to them both, for when I had noted, <hi>That the Line of Deſcent in an Hereditary Kingdom might be interrupted, and yet the Law of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion not broken;</hi> could I be ſuppoſed to mean it of <hi>Rehoboam</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who were nothing related; or of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Adonijah,</hi> who are mentioned in the ſame Paragraph, and where it is obſerved, that the Younger Brother was advanced to the Crown. I have heard, and I find it true, that none are ſo blind as thoſe that will not ſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Concerning a Thorough Settlement.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE are now come to the Mighty Place, and which indeed doth direct us in paying the Duty of our Allegiance; for the Convocation taking notice of the Variation of Governments in the World, having theſe words,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ch.</hi> 28. <hi>P.</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <hi>That when having attained their Ungodly Deſires (whether Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Kings, by bringing any Country into their Subjection, or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105902:16"/>Diſloyal Subjects, by their Rebellions riſing againſt their natural Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign) they have eſtabliſhed any of the ſaid degenerate Forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> viz. <hi>Ariſtocratical, Demecratical,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>amongſt their People; the Authority either ſo unjuſtly gotten, or wrung by force from the True and Lawful Poſſeſſor, being always Gods Authority (and therefore receiving no Impeachment by the Wickedneſs of thoſe that have it) is ever (when any ſuch Alterations are through ſetled) to be reverenced and obeyed, and the People of all ſorts (as well of the Clergy as of the Laity) are to be ſubject unto it, not only for Fear, but alſo for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon I had obſerved, that upon a Revolution from the worſt of Circumſtances, Uſurpation and Rebellion, Obedience to the Eſtabliſhment is acknowledged due. This the Anſwerer takes no notice of, as if it had been nothing concerned in the Cauſe. I then ſhow'd the vaſt Diſpacity betwixt that, their Repreſentation, and our preſent Merciful Deliverance and Settlement; but this alſo he paſſes over. But when I moved here upon the Queſtion, <hi>when a Government may be ſaid to be ſettled,</hi> there he leaps like a Fiſh at a Fly, and becauſe I left out the word <hi>Throughly,</hi> he thinks he has catch'd me Napping; and what if he had, greater than I are ſometimes ſo taken. But did I make any advantage of this Omiſſion, he charges me with none. Did I not, by Settlement, intend as much a Thorough Settlement, as if I had expreſſed it? I am ſure I did. And after all, what they call a <hi>Thorough.</hi> do I not expreſs it by <hi>a Real Eſtabliſhment;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 12.</note> by which (for all he hath ſaid) I cannot yet but mean a Government that is Throughly Settled, for what I ſaid before I repeat again, <hi>That that Government is then Setled, and throughly Setled, when the Crown with all its Dignities, Prerogatives, Adminiſtrations, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, Revenues,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are generally Recognized and perſonally enjoyed; which muſt be ſuppoſed to be, when all Places of Power and Truſt, of Royalty and Importance, are in the Sovereigns hands, and wholly at his Diſpoſal. For to ſay, becauſe there are Foreign Wars, or Secret Plots, that the Crown is not in full Poſſeſſion, ſince there always were, and always will be, diſcontented Parties at home, and Politick Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations abroad, that either actually do, or craftily deſign to diſture the Peace, is to ſay, that no Kingdom ever was, or ever can be Setled.</hi> He ſaw this laſt Period did obviate his Important Objection of <hi>Limerick,</hi> and therefore he wiſely (but how fairly let others judge) quite left it out. But <hi>yet</hi> Limerick <hi>is a Place of Truſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105902:16"/>and therefore the Authors Notion of Settlement will do him no ſervice,</hi> juſt as much as he intended,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 16.</note> and neither more nor leſs. For it will prove as Thorough a Settlement now, as was in Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and ſome other Reigns when ſuch-like places of Importance were in the Enemies hands. But <hi>what becomes of the Poor Iriſh-men,
<note place="margin">ibid.</note> he doubts they muſt be Rebels for all our Authors Demonſtration.</hi> And the Author doubts the Tories will be ſo ſtill, which doubtleſs pleaſeth the Anſwerer, and ſomebody elſe, beſides one that would be call'd Moſt Chriſtian very well: Then for the Reſt, when the Anſwerer tells me, what became of <hi>Jaddus,</hi> whilſt in the Power of <hi>Darius;</hi> I will ſend him back the very ſelf-ſame Anſwer for his ſatisfaction. But a Victorious Army in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſticks on his ſtomack, and tho he is willing to blaſt them, that they may fall before their Enemies; yet neither his Breath or Pen is ſo Omnipotent, and <hi>therefore acknowledging</hi> Ireland <hi>to be a Branch of the Crown of</hi> England,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>annexed to it, and dependent on it,</hi> he plainly juſtifies them. But <hi>Athaliah</hi> is brought on the Stage again, for without her he can prove nothing, and with her he only makes a noiſe.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the Thorough Settlement is made the other Pillar to ſupport their Cauſe, let us enquire what the Convocation inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by it. And ſince he ſays, <hi>There are but two ways to underſtand the Senſe of any Author: The natural and uſual Conſtruction of the words they expreſs themſelves by; and if there be any Obſcurity or Doubt in the meaning of ſome Expreſſions, to interpret them by other Expreſſions, and Aſſertions in the ſame Author;</hi> to which he might have added a third, had he ſo pleaſed, the occaſion of the Authors writing. But becauſe this would abſolutely confute him; by his own Rules, I will try the Controverſie before us.</p>
               <p>Now the natural Conſtruction of the words are very clear and eaſie; that whenever an Uſurper or Rebels have gotten the Authority of a Lawful Poſſeſſor into their hands, and ſo throughly ſettled themſelves, that they are able to hold, and maintain that ſame Authority which they have gotten; he or they, then are to be obeyed. And that they can mean no more by it, than an Ability to maintain the Authority they have got, is plain from the Context, and the whole Chapter, which ſpeaks and treats of Wringing and Forcing this Power out of the hands of the True Poſſeſſor, and thereby throughly ſettling, themſelves. Nay which intimates, <hi>the Uſurper or Rebels
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105902:17"/>having attained their Ungodly Deſires,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 57.</note> to be the Meaſure and Standard of this Thorough Settlement.</p>
               <p>But the Anſwerer runs into Fancies of his own, and will have a Settlement to denote two things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Legality of a Thing, its being according to Law.</hi> Very well!
<note place="margin">P. 18.</note> And is not a King <hi>de Facto, Seignier la Roy,</hi> according to our Laws. He had much better for his own cauſe, have let this Notion of Settlement alone; But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. It denotes a quiet and peaceable Poſſeſſion, without diſturbance from other Claims or Pretenders. Ask his Grace of <hi>Northumberland</hi> this, whoſe Title of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> tho throughly ſettled, and ſo adjudged by the Supream Court in <hi>England,</hi> yet wants not a Pretender, who, they ſay, is again deſigning to make ſome diſturbance about it. And if this be ſo, how ungrounded and unſettled is the Right of thoſe Poor Princes in <hi>Germany,</hi> to whoſe Territories, the Anſwerers and his Maſters Friend and Ally, the <hi>Leviathan</hi> of <hi>France</hi> lays a Claim, and creates Diſturbances. <hi>But the Owner is actually at Law with him, or declares that he will be ſo, ſo ſoon as he hath opportunity, or Money to manage the Suit.</hi> But if Judgment be given, that the Man that is at Suit, is not the Owner. What then? Why! (without Reflection be it ſpoken) a Wrangling Knave, and a Litigious Barreter will never acquieſce.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But there is one word more to be conſidered, and that is throughly,
<note place="margin">ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>Throughly Settled.</hi>
                  </hi> Now what is the <hi>Import of Throughly, but perfectly, to all intents and purpoſes.</hi> Come then, and <hi>let us put theſe together, and the Utmoſt of a Thorough Settlement is, ſuch a Right as is enjoyed plainly, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, without any Contradiction or Objection.</hi> That is, ſuch a Right as never will be in the World, for there is not that Crown upon any Princes Head, but what the variety of Principles amongſt Men of diverſe Parties, will afford them matter of Objections againſt. Such a Cobweb is the Anſwerers Thorough Settlement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His other way of underſtanding the Senſe of an Author, is by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting the Context, and other places, that that was their meaning, and no other.</hi> Now what can you expect from ſuch an Undertaker, but Demonſtration as clear, nay clearer than the Authors; but <hi>Parturiunt montes,</hi> out comes the Caſe of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> for had he not that String, like a Trump Marine to Fiddle on, his Muſick would be at an end. Yet upon this he hangs out a Flag of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105902:17"/>Defiance, and <hi>defies the Author, or any body elſe, to ſhew him one ſingle Inſtance (either in this Chapter, or any where in the whole Book) of any Government that the Convocation requires, and juſtifies Allegiance to be paid to, but what had firſt acquired a Right.</hi> And if by Right, he means a Civil Legal Right (which he muſt, or he ſays nothing) I ſay, and have before proved, That there are as many Inſtances of it, as there are of Revolutions of Government (for the Caſe of <hi>Athalia</hi> I have ſhew'd to be an exempt Caſe,) and to requite him, I defie him, and all his Party, to produce out of this Convocation Book, one Inſtance, wherein Allegiance is denied to be due to <hi>God's Authority, and to be owing to Legal Right,</hi> for <hi>Joaſh</hi> (he by this time knows) is acknowledged to have both.</p>
               <p>I all this while have waited, that the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſhould have made good his ſenſe of the Convocation by other parallel Expreſſions and Aſſertions in the Book, as he promiſed;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 17.</note> but he hath diſappointed me, and if it muſt be done, I muſt do it my ſelf. To work then let us go. And beſides a long continuance, or Preſcription, to which both Parties acknowledge Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to be due; but which in ſudden Revolutions can have no place, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is nothing to our preſent purpoſe. I find the Convocation ſuppoſeth theſe <hi>New Forms of Government</hi> (for ſo they call them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 28. <hi>page.</hi> 59.</note> which intimates that they did not think Continuance to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to their thorough Settlement) to be throughly ſettled.</p>
               <p n="1">I.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 31. <hi>page.</hi> 67.</note> When the People are under the New Governor's Power and Protection; for ſo they affirm of the Jews, <hi>That they were the Subjects of</hi> Alexander, <hi>after his Authority was ſetled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them;</hi> which was when <hi>Darius was vanquiſhed,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 64, 65.</note> but was yet alive, being eſcaped by flight.</hi> Where the ſettlement of his Authority, and his favourable dealing with them (of which the Convocation ſpeaks, but not a ſyllable of his Right) is made the Foundation of their Duty; and they further give this common Reaſon why the Jews were bound <hi>to pray for the long Life and Proſperity both of</hi> Alexander <hi>and his Empire, as they had done of the other Kings,
<note place="margin">ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>Becauſe they lived under their Subjection.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Eſpecially if there be a general Submiſſion of the People; for the want of this is given as one reaſon of <hi>Antiochus</hi> his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment not being ſetled amongſt the <hi>Jews:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ibid.</note> And the acceſs of this, is the only Title whereby <hi>Mattathias</hi> and his Poſterity could claim Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance from the People; for I challenge the Anſwerer to produce out of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation-Book, the intimation of the leaſt Civil Right to it: <hi>For if a Poſſeſſory Right be ſomething, and,</hi> as he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>where there is not better it ought to carry it;</hi> it is plain, that <hi>Antiochus</hi> being poſſeſſed, had the better Legal Title; yet for want of the general Submiſſion of the People, it was not eſteemed ſetled; and therefore <hi>Mattathias</hi> his Claim is preferred before it. Of whom, though there neither was nor could be, our Anſwerer's Preſcription, nor a long undiſturbed Poſſeſſion (the laſt Owner, in our Anſwerer's words, <hi>being actually at Law with him</hi>) nor any Legal Right or Title, but barely the Submiſſion and Conſent of the People (whence he may
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105902:18"/>alſo learn how neceſſary their Conſent is to a Government; yet of him:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 31. <hi>p.</hi> 68.</note> 
                  <hi>After the Jews were delivered from their Servitude under the Kings of</hi> Syria, <hi>and the Government over them was ſetled in</hi> Mattathias<hi>'s Poſterity (the Convocation teacheth, that it was not lawful for the People, upon any occaſion, to have rebelled againſt them, or to have offered vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to their Perſons.</hi> I know the Anſwerer pretends that <hi>Antiochus</hi> had no Right, and 'tis true he had not the Right which the Peoples Submiſſion would inveſt him with; but he had Poſſeſſion, and that is ſuch a Right as our Anſwerer confeſſeth <hi>ought to carry it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 19.</note> If then you deſire to know from the Convocation, what they mean by a <hi>thorough Settlement,</hi> beſide the natural Signification of their words, <hi>Can.</hi> 28. you hence may ſee, That they ſuppoſe that Government to be Thoroughly ſetled, which hath Authority and Power to ſupport it ſelf; eſpecially when owned and acknowledged by the general Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the People, and very cautiouſly is the word <hi>General</hi> made uſe of; for in ſuch Revolutions an <hi>univerſal Submiſſion</hi> is not to be expected.</p>
               <p>Thus I have done with my Anſwerer, and I think, <hi>Plainly demonſtrated Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Obedience to the preſent Powers, to become the Anſwerer's Duty, as well as mine, if he dare ſtick to the Principle of the Convocation; for we have a Government ſo</hi> thoroughly ſetled, <hi>that it can never be unhing'd but with the utter Ruin of our Laws and Liberties, and the Deſolation of the whole Kingdom.</hi> A Government founded upon an Appeal to God for Truth and Juſtice, and ſo founded upon a Divine Right. A Government where if there be any Marks and Notes in Providence of God's poſitive Will and Pleaſure, is ſo characterized and remarked by them (as the Pamphlet doth evidence) that the Anſwerer could not deny them. In ſhort, I hope a Government that is the Reward of our ſteadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and perſeverance in the late Times of Tryal; and may God continue his Bleſſings to us, in continuing it.</p>
               <p>But laying aſide the Convocation, the Anſwerer proceeds to ſhew the Abſurdity of my Interpretation from other Topicks. Now if what I have offered be indeed the ſenſe of the Convocation (and let the Reader judge of it: but if it be ſo) what he beſpatters me with are but ſo many virulent and baſe Reflections upon theſe Venerable Perſons whereof the Convocation did conſiſt. The Reply therefore ſwelling larger than I did expect, I am content to ſit down and hear their Reproach. Only from what I have ſaid, let the Reader ſpeak if he <hi>think the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Paſſive Obedience and Non-reſiſtance to be (what the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer aſſerted) the whole deſign of that part of the Book that concerns Civil Government.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Then for thoſe Worthies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> that ſuffered between the years 42 and 60. a far worthier Pen hath already, and will more fully repreſent the difference betwixt our Caſe and theirs.</p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>Abſurdity of this Doctrine, which</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is, That the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Providence is a Rule of Practice, and a ſufficient Warrant to act contrary to the Rule of Right and Juſtice amongſt Men.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 23.</note> I tell him this is not the Conſequence, but a vile Aſperſion caſt upon the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for the utmoſt that can be extorted from it, is, That the Permiſſion of Providence is a Rule of Practice, and a ſufficient Warrant to Act. Beſides, the Laws of Civil Right and ſtrict Juſtice, when it hath placed Men in ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105902:18"/>that it is not poſſible for them to diſcharge ſome other Duties, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe Laws. And let him touch here if he can or dare, and therefore deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Conſequence till he can better prove it (and I will give him to <hi>latter-Lammas</hi> to do it in) I am not accountable for all that putrid ſtuff that follows.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>As if I taught that Men muſt direct their Lives, not by fixed and ſtated Rules, but by God's Permiſſions and Providential Occurrences, and the like.</hi> All which want as much Honeſty, as they do Ingenuity.</p>
               <p>I purpoſely paſs by his undutiful Inſinuation, of a Thief's having ſtoln a Purſe, and giving it his Neighbour to keep; and then Querying upon it, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ſince he came by it by Providence) he may not keep it.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 24.</note> The Account I have already given, when it is, that Providence is a Rule of Practice, removes this Doubt: Which indeed deſerves another kind of Anſwer than a Pen can give. As alſo ſomething worſe than this, that in his Anſwer may more than once be met with. But I do not mean to turn Informer; nor have I any Stomach to recriminate, elſe I could charge him, and that truly, for building the Doctrines of Right to Crowns in New erected Governments, upon Violence, Bloodſhed and Murther, for he again and again intimates, that if the Royal Line were but extinct, <hi>i. e.</hi> had they Murthered King <hi>James,</hi> and brought him to a Scaffold, when they deſired him but to withdraw; then the preſent Government had acquired a Right, and he could have taken the Oaths with a ſafe Conſcience. Now I believe his Maſter, King <hi>James,</hi> will ken him no Thanks for this his Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Before I cloſe, I muſt obſerve one thing from the Anſwerer, That after all his diſcarding Providence from being an Intimation of God's Will and Pleaſure in any Revolutions; yet upon my Aſſertion, That Predictions themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Interpoſition of Providence are not raſhly to be executed;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 26.</note> for that <hi>David</hi> refuſed to ſtretch forth his Hand againſt the Lords Anointed; waiting his Way and Pleaſure, he confeſſeth,
<note place="margin">ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>That he left it to Gods Providence ſo to order and diſpoſe of things, and to bring it about in ſuch a manner, as he might take the Crown without the Violation if any Duty that he owed, or of any former Engagement he made to King</hi> Saul. <hi>Now when Providence,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>proceeds in this manner, and ſo makes a clear paſſage to Submiſſion; then, and then only, it is a juſtifiable ground to act upon.</hi> I am glad that it is ever a juſtifiable ground to act upon, and doubt not but to ſhew in our caſe, ſomething of a parity to this, for if the taking of the Crown in ſuch a manner, as not to violate any Duty that he owed to others, does make a clear paſſage to Submiſſion, and is a juſtifiable ground then to act upon: pray Sir ſpeak, what Duty was violated by his Sacred Majeſty; or by ſuch as by Oath gave him Aſſurance of their Fidelity, when Providence in ſuch a viſible Divine manner had advanced him to the Throne? They durſt not oppoſe God, whoſe gracious Doing they not only ſuppoſed, but ſo proved it to be, that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer it ſeems, was not ſtiff enough to deny it. And then for His Majeſty, no Obligation of a Subject was upon him, but if he ſuſpected himſelf to be wronged, (and there was violent and unſatisfied Suſpicion of Wrong in the Higheſt Nature, both to himſelf and the whole Kingdom countenanced, abetted, and deſigned to be eſtabliſhed) nothing could reſtrain him from ſeeking his Right
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105902:19"/>but a Tame complying Willfulneſs to ſit down content with his own Loſs, and the Kingdoms Ruin. All that could be pretended to the contrary, is the Unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of ſeeking his Right; for, as <hi>David,</hi> they may ſay, He ſhould have waited till the Lord ſhould ſmite the King, or his day ſhould come to dye, or that he ſhould deſcend into Battle and periſh. As for the laſt, his late Majeſty is reſolved to provide againſt that; but to this I reply, that his then Majeſties Counſels had ſo ordered the Affairs, that they had made it abſolutely neceſſary for his preſent Majeſty then to ſeek his Right or never; in that the Parliament that was to be called, would doubtleſs (by the indirect means that were uſed) have been ſuch as would have acknowledged and confirmed the Impoſtor, and ſo Excluded their preſent Majeſties from the Crown. Add to this his late Majeſties Willful Receſs, and tell me then, <hi>If Providence did not proceed in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as to make a clear paſſage to Submiſſion, and ſo a juſtifiable ground to act upon.</hi> Thus far I ſee no Guilt; then for what the Anſwerer ſeems to inſiſt on, thoſe Active Spirits that had an hand in the Revolution, by deferting the late King <hi>James,</hi> I excuſed them ſo far, that he takes no notice of it, and therefore I again Repeat it, and ſay that his Cauſe in their Conſcience, being Bad, they neither could, nor ought actually to aſſiſt him: An Equity of the Cauſe being neceſſary to the Juſtification of a War. I now ſhould have done, but for full ſatisfaction in the caſe, there is one thing I ought not to paſs by.</p>
               <p>The Anſwerer would make you believe that bare Poſſeſſion is that Authority or Divine Right, that the Author all along ſpeaks of; and ſo an Uſurper my be poſſeſſed of it, an <hi>Athaliah,</hi> or <hi>Antiochus,</hi> or a <hi>Cromwell.</hi> Now the Author thinks, that there are certain Indices and Notes, whereby the Poſſeſſion that he ſpeaks of, and the Authority that is inſiſted on, may eaſily be diſcerned and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed. For the Convocation ſuppoſes a Thorough Settlement, before they Appropriate Obedience to the New Government. So that Poſſeſſion in General cannot challenge the Allegiance, but yet the Authority they ſpeak of may; for want of which Authority both <hi>Athaliah,</hi> and <hi>Antiochus</hi> (though they had got Poſſeſſion) were Rightly oppoſed. Now what theſe Notes are (beſides what is delivered in the Pamphlet) from the Convocation's Notion of a Thorough Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, will eaſily appear. For they requiring the Power, and Protection, or Favourable Dealing of a Prince, and Conſent of the People to compleat a Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, in Oppoſition to theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Uſurped Poſſeſſion ſeldom or never ſuffers the State to enjoy its Rights, Quiet and Protection; ſo that it is in vain, if it weee poſſible, to yield Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Violence, Plunder and Oppreſſion do generally attend Uſurped Poſſeſſion. Law and Juſtice are ſtifled, and Arbitrarineſs rules in all things. Thoſe who do not comply are not permitted to ſit down in Peace, and enjoy the Common Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Protection, but are Haraſs'd, Proſcribed, Perſecuted, and Undone. There is no Connivance, or Favour, but Power and Wilfulneſs manageth all Things; ſo that it is ſcarce poſſible for them to yield a Due and Full Obedience. For beſides that Honour, Reverence and Homage, which (though owing to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power) a Ruin'd, and Oppreſſed Subject can be hardly conceived to Give. The very Oppreſſion it ſelf diſables them from paying Cuſtoms, Taxes and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, which are other Branches of this Allegiance; ſo that the Service of a Liege Subject can ſcarce be given an Uſurper; on the contrary, where it is Authority
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105902:19"/>that is advanced, there the Good of Community is intended, no Violence, Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarineſs, and Injuſtice practiſed, but Law hath its courſe, and every unſuſpected Man his Liberty and Right. This is the very caſe of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> and <hi>Athaliah.</hi> Of the firſt the Convocation-book expreſſeth it. And of the laſt it is to be ſuppoſed that ſhe continued to Rule, as ſhe entred, with the utmoſt Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Violence: nay and the very Reaſon of her Sons Wickedneſs (for which he was puniſhed by God) is imputed to her Inſtigation, in that ſhe is ſaid to be his Counſellour to do Wickedly. And of her, as well as of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> would have eaſed themſelves ſooner, had they but had power, for the Scriptures gives this as the reaſon of her Uſurpation, that the Houſe of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> had no power to keep ſtill the Kingdom. When therefore <hi>Jehoiada</hi> had ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelf with the <hi>Levites</hi> and Officers, he dethroned the Uſurper, and exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Joaſh</hi> to the Crown.</p>
               <p>Secondly, A Uſurpation never meets with a quiet and peaceable Submiſſion of the People, I mean of the great Body of them, for no Revolution can expect them all. There are always powerful Confederacies and Deſigns againſt it, and 'tis only an Intereſted Party that Supports it. You ſhall meet not only with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Murmurings, but loud, open, and (what is worſt of all) moſt juſt and true Complaints. So that Mens Spirits are kept on ſuch a Ferment, that they may be over-awed, but cannot be won to a Willing Submiſſion. But where it is Gods Gracious Doings, you ſhall obſerve ſuch a Chearful Compliance, a ready Homage, and Acclamations ſo Univerſal, that ſuch a Voice of the People can ſcarce be otherwiſe Interpreted, than the Voice of God.</p>
               <p>I deſire the Anſwerer to Scan over the Differences betwixt Gods Permiſſive and his Poſitive Providence, for if I be not groſly deceived, from the Principles that I have laid down; and the Intereſt the People have in Conſenting to the Form of Government, he may, if he pleaſe, diſcern the Difference betwixt 42 and 88. In Uſurpations beſides the Violence committed at the graſping at a Crown, which for the future hardens all Good Mens Hearts againſt it; the Subject, not enjoying Protection under it (as never any but an Intereſted Party do) cannot be thought to be ſo fond of Chains, as to Kiſs and Court them, by paying their Obedience under them, nor do they ever generally own it by ſubmitting Chearfully and Thankfully unto it. Whereas when there is a Revolution upon an Appeal to God for Juſtice and Equity; the Prince treats his People with ſuch Tenderneſs, Care, and Circumſpection, as becomes one that being advanced by, thinks himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to God, for the Truſt he hath committed to him: And on the other hand the People deport themſelves with thoſe returns of Chearfulneſs and Thanks in their Submiſſion, as are befitting a People delivered from Wrong, Tyranny and Slavery. And by this time I hope the Anſwerer hath found out a Difference.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105902:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The Cloſe and Summary of the Whole.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Summ and Subſtance of the Whole is this: God Delegates to Kings Authority and Power, to Govern the People committed to their Charge, in his Stead, and for their Good. And as a King in a Dependent Kingdom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes a Deputy, and Communicates with his Power part of his Name unto him, by making him a Vice-Roy: ſo God by exalting of them to that Great Truſt, makes them, as it were, Vice-Gods; for of them he ſaith himſelf, That they are Gods: And as the Vice-Roy is Reſponſible to none but the King that entruſted him; ſo Kings are only Accountable to God, whoſe Power they have; and in whoſe Stead they Rule: and if they do abuſe his Truſt and Power, (ſeeing no one elſe can) God hath undertaken to call them to an Account for their Miſcariages, ſince (as was ſaid in the Pamphlet) all their Violations of this Truſt reflect upon God, whoſe Truſtees they are. And this is the Reaſon that makes him threaten ſo ſeverely to puniſh Governors, that neglect his Laws, and abuſe his Power. For as the King his Vice Roy, ſo God may Depoſe them at his own Will and Pleaſure. And when they Manage Affairs to his Diſhonour, and the Diſcouragement of Virtue and Probity, as he may, ſo alſo (ſince he himſelf holds the Helms of all Governments in his own hands) it may be ſuppoſed that he will (for the ſake of Juſtice) Animadvert upon them; for ſhall not the God of the Whole Earth do Right? No one elſe can; and therefore He, or none, muſt do it. And when he doth this, it often is by Removing them from that Power and Authority that he had Commiſſioned them with; and (as a King on the Complaint of the Miſgovernment of a Vice Roy) by committing that Charge and Province to Another. For God doth Kings and Emperors no wrong, (though he thus diſplace them) they being Nothing elſe but his Agents and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and to be Employ'd no longer than he knows it to be for the Good of his Church and People.</p>
               <p>When ever therefore (for the ſake of an Oppreſſed people) he is pleaſed thus to Remove and Diſplace an Arbitrary and Uſurping Governor; and raiſe another to his Truſt and Dignity, whom he in his Infinite Wiſdom) foreſees to be more for the Good of his Church, and the Glory of his Providence; all Good people are in Conſcience bound ſubmiſſively to Comply with God's Doing, and yield a Chearful Obedience to his Authority; which where-ever it is, ought to be Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced. Now becauſe the Meaning of God in ſuch Revolutions are often Dark and Ambiguous; for they may be for our Sins, as well as the Sins of our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors: therefore we ought throughly to debate the Caſe in our own Conſcience, and unfeignedly and impartially Examine where the Guilt lies in Us, or in our Governors; for if for ſome conceived diſpleaſure to their Perſons or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we raſhly, and too forwardly withdraw from them that Duty we owe, we do but add Iniquity to Sin. But if we find our ſelves in ſuch Circumſtances,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105902:20"/>that without any ſinful Co operation of ours, a Door is opened for our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; One ſcarce can ſuppoſe it any thing, but God's Gracious Interpoſition. And ſince God doth by his Providence now, what in the days of Prophecy he did by his Immediate Revelations; when we ſee the ſame Events Conſequent upon the ſame Antecedent Cauſes; and God hath plainly told us by his Word that He hath done the One; how can we deny (in a Parity of Cauſes and Events) but that the ſame Hand did alſo the Other. Eſpecially when we ſee the Injured party flying to God for Help; or in the Uſe of the laſt Remedy making his Appeal for Juſtice. This is the Summary of the Whole Caſe, and it would be Hard indeed, if when Deliverance comes upon our Prayers and Tears, We might not embrace it. Let thoſe that hanker after the Onions in an Egyptian Bondage fix their Eyes on them, till the Effluence of the Acrimony force them to Weep; I, for my part, will Wipe mine Eyes and thank God, that there is no Leading into Captivity, and no more Complaining in Our Streets.</p>
               <p>To cloſe up All. Since the force of the Argument runs much upon <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> which the Anſwerer would in this caſe (as a Loofe Sect of Philoſophers, that he knows of, do in others) diſcard from interpoſing ſo far, as to be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement for Men to Act Agreeably to it. I cannot, for all him, but Conclude with a Remarque of the Wonderful Providence of God in Reſerving this Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation-Book, (which was ſo long concealed,) for the Publication of theſe Difficult Times, and the Determination of ſo Weighty a Matter. I will not ſay, what Party put it forth; but there ſeems to be a Providence in that too. But I will ſay, It hath had Good ſucceſs, in Bringing over One, that was the Bulwark of their Cauſe. And that it may prove more and more ſo Succeſsful, in prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Anſwerer, and the Right Reverend the Fathers and Paſtors of This our Too much Divided Church, is the Hearty and Daily Prayers of the Author; which may God Almighty in his own Good Time both Hear and (inſtead of any other) Anſwer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A True Copy of a Letter Writ by King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt, to Dr.</hi> Abbot, <hi>concerning the Convocation called</hi> Anno <hi>1603. 1.</hi> Jac. <hi>and continued by Adjournments and Prorogations to 1610. Now in the Hands of a Gentleman of the Temple.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>Good Dr.</hi> Abbot,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Cannot abſtain to give you my Judgment of your Proceedings in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation as you call it; and both, as <hi>Rex in ſolio,</hi> and <hi>unus gregis in Eccleſia,</hi> I am doubly concerned. My Title to the Crown no body calls in queſtion, but they that neither love you nor me; and you gueſs whom I mean. All that you and your Brethren have ſaid of a King in Poſſeſſion (for that word I tell
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105902:21"/>you, is no worſe than that you make uſe of in your Canon) concerns not me at all. I am the next Heir, and the Crown is mine by all Rights you can name, but that of Conqueſt; and Mr. Sollicitor has ſufficiently expreſſed my own Thoughts concerning the Nature of Kingſhip in General, and concerning the Nature of it, <hi>ut in mea Perſona:</hi> And I believe you were all of his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; at leaſt none of you ſaid ought contrary to it, at the time he ſpoke to you from me. But you know all of you, as I think, that my Reaſon of calling you together, was to give your Judgments how far a Chriſtian, and a Proteſtant King, may concur to aſſiſt his Neighbours to ſhake off their Obedience to their own Sovereign, upon the account of Oppreſſion, Tyranny, or what elſe you like to name it. In the late Queens time, this Kingdom was very free in aſſiſting the <hi>Hollanders</hi> both with Arms and Advice; and none of your Coat ever told me, that any ſcrupled at it in her Reign. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my coming to <hi>England</hi> you may know that it came from ſome of your ſelves to raiſe Scruples about this Matter. And albeit I have often told my Mind concerning <hi>Jus Regium in Subditos,</hi> as in <hi>May</hi> laſt in the Star-Chamber, upon the occaſion of <hi>Hales</hi> his Pamphlet; yet I never took any notice of theſe Scruples, till the Affairs of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> forced me to it. All my Neighbours call on me to concur in the Treaty between <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> and the Honour of the Nation will not ſuffer the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to be abandoned, eſpecially after ſo much Money and Men ſpent in their Quarrel. Therefore I was of the Mind to call my Clergy together, to ſatisfie not ſo much me, as the World about us of the Juſtneſs of my owning the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at this time: This I needed not to have done; and you have forced me to ſay, I wiſh I had not. You have dipped too deep in what all Kings Reſerve among the <hi>Arcana Imperii.</hi> And whatever Averſion you may profeſs, againſt Gods being the Author of Sin, you have Stumbled upon the Threſhold of that Opinion, in ſaying upon the Matter, that even Tyranny is Gods Authority, and ſhould be Reverenced as ſuch. If the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould return to claim his old Pontifical Right to my Kingdom, you leave me to ſeek for others to Fight for it: For you tell us upon the Matter before hand, his Authority is Gods Authority, if he prevail.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Doctor,</hi> I have no time to expreſs my Mind farther in this Thorny Buſineſs. I ſhall give you my Orders about it by Mr. <hi>Sollicitor,</hi> and until then, meddle no more in it, for they are Edge Tools, or rather like that Weapon that's ſaid to Cut with the one Edge, and Cure with the other. I commit you to Gods Protection, Good Dr. <hi>Abhor,</hi> And reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Good Friend</hi> James R.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
